Thank you.
Welcome, everyone, to the Field of Vision video with Jim Dalton.
Thank you for being here today.
And we have a full day to hear Jim share 40 years of market understanding and market experience
and trading experience with us.
And we're all very fortunate to be a part of it.
Jim's taken a lot of time to lay the slides out and the material out in a way that we can fit as much info as possible with our time here today.
And he's also laid it out and put a lot of thought into how to structure it so that it'll flow and you can absorb it and go home and start implementing it in your trading regimen.
Obviously, that's why we're here, to trade better.
And that's how this program was designed for you to go home and trade.
Jim, I've been working with Jim about a year.
And he has asked me to just talk a little bit about the learning process because he's watched me struggle.
And at the same time, he's watched me come to a new level of trading.
And I do believe that this is an edge we develop within ourselves.
It's not an edge from an indicator or a strategy or a methodology.
This is something that we are developing internally, intuitively.
We are developing what we see.
No one can take it from us once we have it.
And to me, that's very exciting because when I am trading well, it's like hitting a golf ball really well.
You change your grip.
It is nothing but hook and slice and pain.
And then one time you hit it and it just feels perfect.
And when I'm trading like that with Jim, that's the feeling.
And it makes it all worth it.
So I just want to throw that out there because it isn't easy and it won't come overnight.
But stick with it because I do believe that we really have a true edge here.
And to utilize 40 years, we don't have to make a new path and reinvent the wheel.
We can learn from someone who didn't have a mentor, who is now here because he wants to offer something that he didn't have and share with us.
I do want to say one other thing that I did hear when I was signing up for this and investing the money.
I was hesitant and a gentleman said to me when I asked him, should I try it?
Should I invest this money?
And he said, absolutely.
And he had no vested interest in Jim Dalton.
He said, you will never look at the markets the same way again.
And I can genuinely say that from a year ago when I started, I will never look at the markets the same way again.
And there's much more depth and there's much more interrelationships I consider.
And the longer I go through it, the more it becomes more intuitive and natural to me.
And I'm very grateful to be a part of it.
So with that, if you will help me welcome Mr. Jim Dalton.
Julia, thank you.
Thank you very much.
I've watched Julia go through this process and we were doing an intensive out in Napa.
It was the last day of the intensive.
We had about an hour to go.
And I looked out and she was kind of leaning over the desk.
Her eyes were about this big.
And I knew at that point in time that the information that we have talked about had absolutely overwhelmed her.
And it was really at that point that she really made the turning point.
I talked to her the following week.
And that turning point came and you could see the growth take place.
One of the best compliments I think we've ever received, Rick in the middle was telling me yesterday about one of the blogs that he was reading.
And one of the blogs, somebody asked about the program that we offer.
And they said, no, it was too complex and too complicated.
It wasn't for them.
That is probably the finest compliment we've ever received because that is 100% true.
If it was, Julia said it, if it was easy, there would be no edge.
If there was easy, if it was easy, it would be replicated almost overnight.
It is not easy.
It is a process that you will go through.
But understand that the rewards are huge if you make it.
Not many people are going to make the entire process.
But we're trying to give you a foundation.
Once you have that foundation, then you start to build on the foundation.
Let's start off and let's just begin to review some of the basics that are involved.
The tool that we use is called Market Profile.
However, Market Profile is simply a tool.
What we are talking about is about trading and all of the intricacies and the interrelationships that occur when you're trading.
So many people want to know only where do I get in and where do I get out.
It is clearly not that simple.
It is far more complex than that.
What we talk about is trading.
We use the Market Profile.
We call it the Market Profile graphic.
And you'll see as we develop it is when you look at a graphic, a graphic is something that brings together many complex points at one time.
The most famous graphic in the world is the graphic of Napoleon's army going into Russia.
From just one simple graphic, you see the size of the army as Napoleon started.
You see how the army shrinks, you see the temperature change, you see the distribution of food.
From one simple graphic, the most famous graphic in the world, you can understand an awful lot of very complex information in a way that our minds are very welcoming.
We welcome looking at graphical type of information.
And so this is what, when we get to the Market Profile graphic, you will see that it is in fact very similar to this famous graphic.
Okay, let's take a look and start off.
This is just to get you started.
This gives you some idea of where we're going to be when we're all done.
Remember, this is not basic right here.
This is kind of how we look at days.
For example, up at the top, you'll see something labeled afternoon pullback low.
If you have a trend day, a trend day being a day where the market has moved rapidly, say to the upside,
very often late in the afternoon, you will get a pullback or you'll get a little inventory correction.
Most people have no idea the significance of that very minor point where the market pulled back.
That reference point, late in the afternoon, until it's taken out, nothing's really changed in the marketplace.
So we're going to talk about that.
We're going to talk about the significance of how do you identify when change takes place.
We look along here and we look at significant highs and lows.
Triple references.
We look at what you're going to be introduced to is called the point of control.
Point of control or the fairest price at which business is being conducted.
It's very important.
If the fairest price at which business is being conducted throughout the day doesn't change,
then you don't have a lot of change in the market.
Sometimes you'll see that start to migrate.
So all this is just some idea of where you're going to be when we're done with this.
That is a point of control right there.
You'll understand the significance of that or the fairest price to do business as we complete this.
You'll understand the importance of the references.
Anyhow, this just gives you some feel of what it's going to look like and what you're going to start to understand as we get to the last portion of this presentation.
Okay, let's take a look structure.
Another comment in here that you're going to understand.
If you think back and visualize a bar chart, most people that have ever traded look at a bar chart.
A bar chart is a straight line.
On that bar chart, you have an open, high, low, and close.
Okay, you have basically four data points.
You have no dimension to that bar chart.
When you look at a profile, and we haven't explained to you yet how you build a profile,
but you can look and see that it is not a straight line.
When we add another dimension, we get into what we call market structure.
We will be talking about what is strong structure, what is weak structure.
Just a few days ago, the market had a historic break.
The Dow was down over 1,000 points late in the afternoon on a huge drop,
and then the market rebounded over 700 points before you knew what time it was.
If the underlying structure of that market had been strong,
I suspect we would not have had that kind of break.
Those that have been looking at the material that we've done for some period of time
know that I've been writing about the risk inherent in weak market structure.
But you'll start to learn about structure.
You'll learn what it means.
You'll also learn, just as you would if you had a house with shindles on it and you had a leak,
you'll start to learn how do you repair that house.
How do you repair or what happens to repair poor structure in the marketplace.
I don't expect you to understand any of this right now.
All I want to give you is a flavor of the depth of which we're going to get to
before we complete this process.
Okay, at its foundation, the market is simply a two-way auction process.
The motives and incentives of the buyers and sellers are infinite.
But let's talk a little bit about an auction process so you get a feel for it.
Most people have been to some kind of an auction.
Generally, the auctions you've been to are maybe an art auction.
Or at one time, years ago, I had a client that owned the Galleria down in Texas.
When he used to come in to the programs, he would fly in on his own plane.
He would take the whole floor of one of the hotels.
And he'd been to three or four of the programs.
And I said, you know, you keep coming back.
I said, how is this working for you?
He said, well, you know, Mr. Dalton, he said, I'm still not doing a wonderful job of trading the market.
But he said, in my life, he said, I buy ponies at the auctions all the time.
And he said, they're sure not getting the best of me at the auctions for the ponies anymore.
He said, I know what's going on.
And he said, I can't tell you what you've done for me, learning to understand how an auction really functions.
And he said, I thought I knew.
Well, let's walk through an auction process.
In a traditional auction process, it goes one way.
Let's start with kind of an expensive art object.
If the auctioneer is trying to get the auction started at, say, $100,000, what happens if nobody will lift the bid at $100,000?
What does the auctioneer have to do now?
He's got to lower the bid, right?
So he lowers the bid.
And he may have to lower the bid down to $92,000 before the auction can get underway.
So all of a sudden, he lowers it to $92,000.
And all of a sudden, the bidding starts.
You got $93,000, I got $94,000, I got $95,000, $97,000.
And sometimes it will tear right back through the original $100,000 level that no one would lift the bid for to begin with.
Now, as the auction progresses, you may hear a couple of things.
As the auction starts to slow down, the auctioneer has to make it feel exciting and really keep your interest, right?
So he starts putting in what is called filler.
So let's say the auction slows down at $105,000.
Who will give $105,000?
And he goes into this elaborate description.
And at that point in time, is the auction over?
No, the auction's not over.
But the auction is slowing down.
You need to, if you really become aware of this, you understand what's going on.
The same thing takes place in the markets.
What happens, what other kind of response might you hear from the auctioneer?
Let's say you're up to $105,000, and, you know, you've done your homework, and you're pretty smug, and you think it's certainly not worth $105,000.
But at $105,000, all of a sudden, you hear the auctioneer say, new bidder.
Well, are higher prices cutting off activity, or are higher prices bringing in more bids and more activity?
When you hear the auctioneer say, new bidder, higher prices are bringing in more activity, not cutting off the activity.
Guess what?
It doesn't make any difference what you think that value is.
That auction's not completed.
How many times in a market have you seen price go down, whether it's a stock or whether it's a future?
You will see price go down, and all of a sudden, out of nowhere, the price reverses and is going the other way.
And you start to see that higher prices, instead of cutting off activity, bring in more and more activity.
So one of the things that you really start to need to understand and appreciate is this whole idea of the auction process.
This is how markets operate.
The first example we talked about was a very simple example.
It's a very expensive art auction.
One item to be auctioned.
Okay?
Let's go and talk about where horses are being auctioned.
Horses are being auctioned.
It may not be, there may be multiple, you know, horses or livestock available for auction.
Now, the same process as the auction gets underway, some people are getting their demand fulfilled, right?
So they're dropping by the wayside, and this auction continues, and the auction continues up until what?
Until the demand has been filled or everybody has stepped aside.
So we go up until the last bitter bid.
And that's when the auction is completed.
Now, think about this.
If the auction was completed successfully, and I now walk out and I say,
Oh, by the way, I have one more of the same thing to auction.
If the auction had been successful, and let's say that this item went for, pick a number, $150,000.
If the auction was successful, I say, Oh, by the way, I have one more.
Probably shouldn't get any more than $120,000, $125,000, because the auction ought to go up,
and it ought to drop away from it very quickly once it's completed.
So this is kind of the auction process.
Extremely important in understanding how markets operate.
Now, the difference between the art auction or the auction for livestock or multiple items
is that in the stock market, we continually, or futures market, we continually auction from low to high and from high to low.
So that ongoing auction process is continuous in there.
If you go to the art auction, for example, you have all types of people that are participating, right?
And this becomes very important also.
You may have a dealer that is at one of the auctions.
It could be the art auction, or it can be in the auction for livestock.
You may have a dealer that's trying to get inventory for his business, and then he's going to do what?
Resell it.
So that would be one motivation.
You may have a collector, right?
You may have a collector, and he wants that for his own personal collection.
Maybe it's a legacy thing, or maybe it's an ego type of thing.
The motivations go on and on.
We talk a lot about, in this time frame, motivation and why, who are the buyers and sellers in these auctions.
In the stock and futures market, we auction from low to high and then from high to low in this continual search for information.
When the market auctions too high, at that point in time, you start to feel that it was too much.
Once it gets too high, then the process starts in the opposite direction, and we start auctioning lower, looking to attract what?
If we start auctioning lower, we are searching for what?
Now, for buyers, right, as we're auctioning higher, we're looking for sellers.
So in this process, this up-and-down two-way auction process is generated a tremendous amount of information, and it's that kind of information that we want to capture.
Okay, let's take a look at this process.
Right here, all this is, and we haven't explained it yet, but this is a market profile.
In the one on the left, on this profile, and we've split it out, your first auction is going from high to low, right?
So the market started high, it auctioned lower.
Down here, it finally got low enough.
When you auction lower, you're looking for what?
You're looking for buyers.
You got low enough to find buyers, and now you start auctioning in the other direction.
When you auction in the other direction, you're looking for what?
You're looking for sellers.
It's that two-way auction process.
What you're going to find is we use the market profile in order to record the net effect of that two-way auction process.
So this is what it looks like when it's completed.
This is what it looks like when it's spread out.
And I just put it this way so you can see the auction going lower, looking for buyers, the auction going higher, looking for sellers.
And you can see that there is, if you had a bar chart, you'd never see this, right?
We talked earlier about a bar chart, one dimension.
All we've done is added another dimension.
We're going to show you how this is constructed in just a moment.
Okay, the following graphic represents a normal distribution curve.
Scientists for years have employed a distribution curve in order to organize the data.
They employ the curve to organize data and then so they can study the data.
That's the purpose of it.
It's a scientific approach to understanding data.
All we've done, this is what's called a normal or a bell-shaped curve.
Now, I can tell you that it is very rare that you will ever see a normal or bell-shaped curve in the marketplace.
But it's the idea of the distribution.
What we do, if we start off and we look at a bell-shaped curve, that would be a market that was perfectly balanced.
Now, what we start to observe is how far out of balance the market is in either direction.
When you look at the curve, one standard deviation is going to cover approximately 70%.
They give you an actual number of 68%, but it's going to cover about 70%.
One standard deviation, the fattest part of the curve.
Two standard deviations, about 95% of the curve.
When you get into three standard deviations, it's going to cover about 99% of the curve.
Well, you don't need to worry about those numbers.
It is just this idea of how information is distributed.
What you're going to find is the market profile graphic really is keyed off of the idea of a normal distribution curve.
It is nothing more than a way to organize data.
Once the data is organized, now you have a way to start to understand what is going on.
And you understand, if you look at a market, and one day you've got maybe 100,000 participants,
the next day you've got 150,000 participants, it's all going to vary.
If you, let me give you a real-life example.
Let's say I have a barbecue in my backyard, and I've invited 30 people to that barbecue.
And I'm looking out, everybody seems to be having fun, and I look out and I say,
Rick, what do you think the average or mean height is of the people at my barbecue?
He looks at me and he says, Jim, how would I know?
All I do is I go out and I take that same data, I take those 30 people, I organize them under a distribution curve.
All of a sudden, you start to look at it, he says, oh, well, it looks to me like the average or mean height is maybe it's around 5'7 or 5'8.
Now, let's say we take a picture, we take a picture or a snapshot, a satellite flies over,
takes a picture of those organized people at my barbecue.
Now, some people leave early, right?
Some people come in a little bit later.
Those that leave early have some height, those that come in later have a different height.
Maybe more left than come back in.
So, maybe the following morning or late that night, I go out and I reorganize those people again,
and I take another satellite photo of the people at my barbecue.
All of a sudden, I take one picture, I take the other, and I overlay those two pictures.
They're probably not going to be the same, right?
So, what it's going to allow me to see is some shift that took place in the underlying data.
Had I not organized that data, the chances are that I wouldn't have seen or been able to determine
subtle shifts that took place in the people attending that barbecue.
That's what we're after.
We're after the ability to organize data and take that data and start to make some sense out of it.
Okay, let's take a look at how we actually form the market profile graphic.
When, in order to form a distribution curve, you need two things.
You need a variable, and you need a constant.
The breakthrough in the ability to organize the data was the discovery by an individual by the name of Pete Stonelmeyer.
It was majored in statistics at Stanford.
The breakthrough was that you can make time the constant.
So, this time between 11 and 11.30 is the same as the time between 12 and 12.30.
One day is as long as the next day, one week as long as the next week, etc.
So, you make time the constant.
Time the constant forms your horizontal axis.
If you then take price, which is a variable, and plot price the variable against time the constant,
you have the makings of formulating a distribution curve in order to organize the data that we're going to be talking about.
When Pete came up to talk to me some years back, we had been talking for probably less than four minutes.
When Pete threw out the idea of time as a constant, I knew immediately what he had been discovered.
I had been trying to find a way to organize the data.
I actually had some things on my desk that looked like distribution curves.
At that point in time, I was trying to figure out, you know, how to do certain option strategies.
But I knew immediately, I knew my stuff didn't work like it should.
I knew that Pete had something when he came in the idea of time as the constant.
We talked for another 15 or 20 minutes.
Pete walked out to the elevator, walked back in, and he looked at me and said,
Would you like to sponsor my first book?
The name of the first book that introduced this information was called Markets and Market Logic.
And I said yes, and on the spot, I wrote him out a check for $10,000.
If you ever look at the first book, right across the front, it said sponsored by J. Abdul.
But I knew the value of the idea of making time the constant.
So many great discoveries are far simpler than we would ever imagine.
So time the constant versus price the variable allows us to form the distribution curve.
If you take, there's a profile, all it is, you start to visualize,
it's nothing more than the distribution curve we looked at earlier turned on its side.
That's how we organize the data.
Now, that's what a market profile looks like.
If you look, if you think about this, if you have a bar chart,
and we already said a bar chart has four data points, right?
Open, high, low, close.
When you look at a profile that is two-dimensional, it is going to release tremendous amounts of information.
Now, not only do I still have the open, high, low, close on this, right?
But I now get some performance figures.
I can see how much time, the more letters out here, the more time that was spent here,
I start to get some idea of how much time was spent at each price.
How much time was the auction down here?
It was rejected pretty quickly.
At the top, it was rejected pretty quickly.
So, I get tremendous amounts of information that I didn't have before.
Remember, initially, with one dimension, open, high, low, close, that's really what I was dealing with.
Now, tremendous amounts of information.
That, to some people, is a negative.
Sometimes, if you can't process basic information to begin with,
giving you more information is not necessarily a positive.
You have to really be able to learn to use the information,
which means you're probably going to have to get rid of some other information in order to make room for this.
So, on its surface, while it intuitively may sound good that more information is better,
it is not necessarily true.
You have to use that information very intelligently.
Okay, let's work forward.
And we see now, the graphic is just, it's an analogy as to putting the pieces of a puzzle together.
As you go through this, it's piece by piece by piece.
I would guess, if you're really pretty sharp, it's going to take you probably a good year,
a good year, to start to get a foundation of how all these pieces begin to fit together.
We have a saying, and you'll hear it again, and you'll see a slide on it later,
no real learning starts until you can put that information within some contextual view.
Give me an idea.
Most people, it's always amazed me,
I will get a tremendous number of clients that have been very successful in business.
In business, if you raise the price of your product,
and your volume drops off, what do you do?
You're going to lower the price, right?
You raise the price of your product, and the volume drops off,
your market share drops off,
you're going to lower the price to get back your market share.
Those that have been in business,
if you raised your price too high, and your volume dropped off,
are you going to get your market share back by just going back to the original price?
Probably not, right?
You're probably going to have to lower it below where you were initially,
in order to get your market share back, and get your business back.
Now, sometimes we can see that by actually lowering the price,
or we can offer discounts.
You know, 0% financing, $500 cash back,
there's all kind of ways in order to adjust the price,
in order to get the demand that you want.
That same kind of thing takes place in a market.
So, let's talk about this idea of context.
Many people, when they come out of business,
they understand context tremendously.
They understand price, they understand volume,
yet they will turn around and start to trade stocks and futures,
and they will focus mainly on price.
They don't pay attention to volume.
If I raise my price and my volume drops off by 20%,
guess what?
In business, I know immediately that's not very healthy.
The structure of what I've done with that price isn't going to last very long.
Does that mean I won't sell anything?
No, I'll sell something, but it's not going to be the same thing.
Or, if I raise my price, if I raise the price,
and I actually do the same or more volume,
does that give me information?
That gives me a whole entirely different context.
The best example that I can think of is years ago,
I used to be amazed.
You'd watch the interest, you'd watch interest rates.
And if interest rates were coming down,
all of a sudden, people would be looking and say,
well, I'm not going to buy the house right now
because I think rates are going lower.
So, you know, it's going lower and lower,
and all of a sudden, finally, the Fed tightens the rates
and the rates start to go higher.
Well, theoretically, as the rates go higher,
theoretically, that should cut off the activity, right?
But, in fact, if you're coming from this low level,
when you raise the rates, does that cut off the activity?
No, they come clamoring into the market
because they're afraid that the rates
are now going the other way.
So higher prices bring in even more activity
because people are afraid they're going to miss the market.
Now, think about this in the stocks and futures market.
The price goes down and goes down,
and you're not going to buy, right?
You're not going to buy.
The market's going down because it's going lower, right?
All of a sudden, it starts the other way,
and you start paying more and more and more.
Or something you could have bought for $7 yesterday,
you're willing to pay $9, $10, and $11 for today
because you're caught in this auction process
and you want to make sure you don't miss it.
That's all part of the contextual view.
So I want you to think about those things,
those pieces of the puzzle.
Now, let's, for those that are new to this process,
let's talk about the construction of a market profile.
First of all, each letter,
and you'll see how the letters are formed in a minute,
each letter is called a time price opportunity, TPO.
It is just simply a way to record the data.
It means nothing more than that.
It doesn't make any difference if it's an A, a B, or a C.
Okay, let's take a look at the next step
in how we start to put this together.
Initializing the initial balance,
or when we put this together,
on each, the way we have done it here,
is each period is in 30 minutes.
So, for example, if a market, the S&Ps,
open at, I believe it's 8.30, we're in Chicago,
I think they open at 8.30, Chicago time.
So, for the first half hour of trading,
we might use the letter A.
So, that would, so, every time it trades at a given price,
we just put a letter to show that we traded at that price.
The second period would be B.
All we're doing is recording
every time the second period trades at a price.
Then you've got C, et cetera.
So, it goes on.
So, we traded at this price in only one 30-minute period.
We traded at this price in three 30-minute periods.
And this is the profile, how it starts to form.
Or, if you think of our puzzle,
it starts to put the left edge to the profile.
And then you'll see that the dimensions,
or the dynamics, move to the right.
Okay, the structure, this is what we refer to
as the structure of the market.
As we record this information,
we start to see the structure forming in the marketplace.
For example, we talked about the auction process to begin with.
If we traded down here, this was the second period low,
and the low of the third period, C period, was up there.
What happened when prices were going lower,
you're advertising for what?
You're advertising for buyers, right?
Did they find buyers?
They found buyers down there,
and they were fairly aggressive,
because the next period, that's the lowest price trade.
You now have some type of information about the marketplace.
You auctioned low enough.
You got the expected return,
and the expected return was to find buyers.
Now, the auction, here's the auction,
and now you see the auction starts in the opposite direction.
So it tried to go lower.
That auction, we said it's a two-way auction process.
It tried to go lower.
It got the expected response.
The expected response when you go lower
is to find buyers.
It found the buyers.
Now, the market's going higher,
and as the market's going higher,
it's advertising for what?
It's advertising for sellers, right?
And it goes up until it can find those sellers.
That's just, we're going to continue to work on this,
but that's just kind of the process.
I want you to relate it.
I want you to relate it to the auction process.
Think about the two-way auction process,
and start thinking about,
we organize data in order to gather what?
When we organize the data,
what do we want from that data?
Information, right?
Now, we call that information market-generated information.
Now, have I found any information right here?
I found information.
I found that there were buyers at that level, right?
And guess what?
It's not somebody's opinion.
It's not somebody on the news telling you anything.
This is real.
This happens with real people,
with real money,
and that's what we're recording.
It's not somebody's view on the tube or a talking head.
This is supported by real money, real activity.
Now, as we go on,
we're going to want to know how much volume was here,
how aggressive it was.
Let me just ask you a business question.
If, in fact,
this low price down here was a good price,
how long should that price have been there?
Momentarily, right?
Now, let's say we get down here,
and if it's only there momentarily,
how much volume should there be?
Very little.
It ought to move away from there very quickly.
All of a sudden, I get a lot of volume.
It's there a long time.
You have a whole different context.
Okay, let's continue on
and to see how this develops.
We have, let me go back one slide.
I talk about something in here.
Initial balance.
Initial balance is really
the first two periods of the day.
Now, it doesn't have to be an exact definition.
Okay?
Initial balance is just something we're saying
when the market opens in the morning,
what is really,
how are people seeing the market?
Are they auction a little bit lower?
They find some buyers.
They auction a little bit higher.
They find some sellers.
So, you have a little bit of balance in the morning.
It's not an absolute type of thing.
It doesn't have to actually be two periods.
It is just to give you a foundation.
Once you have that initial balance,
then what you want to see is,
as the day goes on,
are you getting outside of that range?
So, if your initial balance,
let's say, for example,
was from 1 to 10,
and then as the day goes on,
you start trading at 11, 12, 13, 14.
So, you're going beyond the initial balance.
You're extending that range.
And who's extending the range?
Is it buyers or sellers?
It's going to be buyers
that are extending that range to the upside.
So, again, it releases more information
about what's going on in the market.
Okay.
Let's take a look.
And this is what we would call range extension.
So, we have the first two periods,
A, B, in this example.
So, the first two periods would be our initial balance.
Now, the market extends down in C period.
When it extends down in C period,
okay, it found,
as we talked already,
it found what?
It found buyers.
Now, once we find the buyers there,
the market starts to trade back up.
When it starts to trade back up again,
now it's going to start searching
for the other end of that initial balance.
Does it have to get there?
No.
But it's get this idea
of the flow of the auction process.
Okay.
Let's kind of move on.
We've just talked, again,
another piece of the anatomy
or the description
would be called a buying tail.
Okay.
A buying tail is nothing more
than a way to say
that the buyers were what?
Aggressive?
They were very aggressive
at that level.
So,
a two-tick buying tail,
three-tick timetail,
four-tick buying tail,
all is a different measure
of how aggressive,
how aggressive the buyers were
at that particular level.
Again,
that's information.
Now,
let me stop for a second.
What happens
when people are first
looking at this information?
They want to run out
almost immediately
and look for a stock
or a future
that has a buying tail.
Oh, boy.
I mean,
I did this.
When I first started
to learn about this,
I would go out
and I would look for something,
a buying tail.
Oh,
I've got aggressive
buying in there.
And if I didn't have
a buying tail
and I found myself
unwilling to buy
because I didn't have
the sign of the aggressiveness
of that.
This is one data point.
It is one piece
of information.
It is not in context.
Let me,
we're very early
in this process,
but let me complicate this.
What does it mean
if there is no buying tail?
Okay?
It may mean several things.
And this is when we talk about
it takes time
to understand
this information
and to be able
to use it effectively.
Sometimes,
if a market is too short,
we've heard,
we've all heard
the phase,
that a market
is too short
to go any lower
or too long
to go any higher.
Sometimes,
there's so many people
that are short the market,
that have sold the market short,
that every time
the market goes down,
they're buying
to cover their short.
So the market may be weak,
but it may have to rally
before it can break
because you have to get
some of that inventory.
When markets are too short,
it's nothing different.
If you think about a business,
it's nothing different
than saying
that a merchant
has too much inventory.
In this case,
the traders have
too much short inventory.
And that inventory
has to be balanced.
The same thing
on the upper end,
sometimes we say
a market has to break
before it can rally.
Sometimes,
it's because
there's too much
long inventory up there.
Too many people
nervous
and they're looking
for places to sell
or at the bottom
looking for places
to cover their short.
That's inventory.
Every trader's
got an inventory.
You can come in
in the morning
with zero position,
you have zero inventory.
You short a contract,
you short one.
You buy one,
you long one.
That's your inventory.
You start taking
that in total
around the world
and all of a sudden
you can get
huge inventory imbalances.
So,
one of the things
you'll learn later on
and comes with
cumulative experience
is you find out
there's also information
in when there is
no buying tail.
Anyhow,
we're not here
to talk about that now.
All I'm trying
to warn you against
right now
is that
it is not as simple
as it looks.
I think about the time
when I was in the service
and the first class
we had on
hand-to-hand combat
and martial arts
and things like that
and I remember
the Sergeant Montgomery
saying,
gentlemen,
let me warn you,
you know,
if you go out
in the bars tonight,
you don't know enough
to really put this to use.
Of course,
we were fast learners,
right?
So we go out
the first night
we're down in
one of the Navy SEAL areas
down in
the southern part
of the country
and we got
Wise Marken
in a bar
and guess what?
We learned very quickly
we did not have
enough information
at that point in time
to compete
with some of the Navy SEALs.
I did come out alive
but it was not
that pleasant
to experience.
I had some
unpleasant experiences
here early on.
Okay?
Let's move on.
We talked earlier
about a buying tail.
Now,
we come up
and we talk
about a selling tail.
It's just the
mirror image.
Again,
it's information.
The longer the tail,
the more aggressive
the sellers were
at that point in time.
That is a very
valuable type
of information.
And as you can see,
as the day develops,
you continue to get
dimension to the profile.
Okay?
Let's continue
to look at the anatomy.
Down here,
picture before
we had the C period.
Down here,
we circled this
so you were right here.
When you don't have
the buying or selling tails,
what we're saying
is the puzzle
at this point
is not yet completed.
very key piece
of information.
For example,
you will see some days
where you'll get right there
and you have ABC.
The market will rally
from that level.
And let's,
a lot of times,
this may turn out
to be a previous day's
high or low.
A very mechanical point
that traders
can very easily see.
So you'll see the market
rally from here.
What it does,
it changes the odds
of the market
going higher.
It may bounce
from there.
You may get some short
covering from there.
You may get some traders
mechanically buying
at a previous
morning low
or daily low.
But the fact
that the auction
is not complete here
lowers the odds
of your success
to the upside.
Very often,
what you'll see
is not completed.
You'll see it bounce.
Then you'll see it
come back a second time
and actually complete
that auction process.
Again,
it's going to get
more complicated.
But it's just
a piece of information.
But it helps
as we go through this.
It helps compute
the odds
of being long,
being short.
Trading is about,
trading is about
understanding the odds.
Most people
have no idea
when they're trading
what the odds
they're dealing with are.
All they want to do
is they're so
emotionally involved
they just want to
buy something lower,
sell it higher.
They have no idea
that the risk
they're taking.
The other day
when the market
dropped, you know,
a thousand points
at one time,
we were talking
about poor structure
going up.
Most of the people
had no idea
the risk that they had
by being long
the market.
When you look
underneath the market,
there was weakness
in the structure.
Would I have
predicted that?
No, I wouldn't
have predicted that
because it was
far beyond
three, four, five.
It was probably
an uncalculable event.
a 50 standard
deviation move
when you had
a break like that
which may be
equivalent to
the odds of that
happening in our lifetime
are probably,
you know,
minuscule.
but the odds
of having
something bad
happen were
much greater
because of the fact
of the underlying
structure
and we'll continue
to come back
to that.
Okay, let's look
at more pieces
that go into
the puzzle.
I talked earlier
about the point
of control
and this will be
a very important
concept for you
to deal with
as we go
through this.
Technically speaking,
when you look
at the market
profile,
the point of control
is the longest
line reading
from left to right
of the daily
profile.
It's the longest
line means
it traded there
in the greatest
number of half
hour periods.
Incidentally,
we use 30 minute
periods to construct
the market profile.
That's on when
you go across
the horizontal line
in the bottom.
The first period
would be 30 minutes
so if a market
opened at 9.30
the first period
would be 9.30
to 10.
The second period
would be 10
to 10.30.
It doesn't make
any difference.
You can use
5 minutes,
15 minutes,
an hour.
You can do it
with a day.
You can have
each period
being a day.
It doesn't make
any difference.
One of the
important points
that I want
to make here,
when you go
through this,
the concepts
that we are
talking about,
the organization
of the data,
the way the market
works,
if it doesn't
work for all
time frames,
and we haven't
really introduced
the time frames yet,
but you can
quickly understand
that there's
people with
very short
time frames
and people
with very long
time frames,
day traders,
people that are
going to buy
for months.
The concepts
are exactly
the same,
whether it's
5 minute,
5 minute time frame,
30 minute time frame,
daily time frame,
all markets
that are
financial in
nature should
operate in
exactly the
same manner.
We'll talk
about that
more as we
go.
The first
we had was
the point of
control.
It's the
longest line,
closest to the
center of the
range.
That's the
technical
definition.
But what I
want you to
really appreciate
more than
anything else,
it is the
fairest price
at which
business is
being conducted.
If I'm
looking at
a graphic,
a profile
graphic for
a particular
day,
the longest
line closest
to the
center of
the range
is the
fairest price
at which
business is
being conducted
for that
particular day.
That is
extremely
valuable
information.
As you
see,
price move
away from
the fairest
price to
the downside
or move
away from
it on
the upside,
let's add
some context.
If the
fairest price
is moved
right here
and now
you see
price start
to auction
higher to
get away
from the
fairest price,
what would
it take
to change
the fairest
price?
This is
formed by
time,
right?
So if I
spent five
periods here
in the
middle and
then four
at the
next price,
it would
take time
in order to
raise or
lower the
fairest price
to conduct
business.
But if I
start to
move away
from the
fairest price,
or another
way to say
I have
price moving
above value
or above
the fairest
price,
and let's
say it's
on low
volume.
If I
move away
from the
fairest price
to do
business
on low
volume,
what do
you think
the odds
are that
that price
change is
going to
be maintained?
If I
moved away
on lower
volume,
not very
good,
right?
No
different
than a
merchant
or a
manufacturer
raising the
price of
a product
that they're
offering
and having
the volume
dry up.
The chances
are you're
going to get
regression
back to
the mean.
The same
thing if
price goes
lower and
the volume
dries up
or diminishes,
the chances
are you're
going to get
pulled back.
Now,
let's talk
about a
different
scenario.
My
fairest
price to
do
business
here and
then price
moves higher.
As it
moves higher,
that's going
on increased
volume.
What do
you think
the chances
are now?
You see how
the odds
change?
It may
get pulled
back to
this,
but the
odds have
lessened.
If I'm
moving higher
away from
the fairest
price on
solid volume,
the odds
are less
that I'm
going to
regress
back to
this level.
Again,
this is all
part of the
context and
we'll continue
to work on
this.
The point
of control
or the
fairest
price to
do
business
will
migrate
up or
down
throughout
the day.
As you
look at
the profile,
you can
see another
way to
describe the
market profile,
it is a
time-sensitive,
real-time,
time-sensitive
evolving
database.
It's
alive,
it's
dynamic,
it changes
throughout the
day.
We said
each one
of those
letters
is the
TPOs.
As the
TPOs
change,
it's
dynamic,
it grows
with you,
with the
market.
There's
absolutely
nothing
static
about it.
The
migration
of the
point of
control
up or
down
throughout
the day,
in other
words,
if the
fairest
price to
conduct
business
migrates
up and
down
throughout
the day,
that is
also
generating
very
valuable
information.
If,
in fact,
you start
to see
the
point
of
control
migrating
lower
throughout
the day,
what is
causing it
to migrate
lower?
Is it
because of
buyers?
Or is it
because of
sellers?
When you're
on the
floor of
exchange,
this means
buy,
sell.
If you
have a
point of
control
migrating
lower
throughout
the day,
that means
that you
have
somebody
selling
into the
market.
In other
words,
what they're
probably
doing is
on every
rally,
you probably
have some
bigger money
saying,
you bought
some,
they let
the market
settle,
it comes
up again,
you bought
some more,
be very
subtle,
but all
of a sudden,
you see
that fairest
price at
which business
can be
conducted
migrating
lower.
Then,
all of a
sudden,
what you'll
see sometimes
is you'll
just see
the market
give way
and you'll
see a big
spike to
the downside
because all
of a sudden,
it started
out very
subtle,
right?
If you're
really a
smart seller
and you've
got any
size,
you want
to disguise
your intentions
as much
as you can,
right?
You really
want to
disguise it.
You don't
want the
world to
know what
you're
doing.
If you're
Fidelity
or Magellan
or somebody
in Vesco
like that,
you don't
want to
advertise what
you're
doing.
Matter of
fact,
it's not
uncommon for
these people
to spread
their orders
out or do
everything they
can to
disguise them.
So all
of a sudden,
you see this
point of
control or
fairest price
to do
business
migrating
lower.
All of a
sudden,
the world
wakes up and
they say,
uh-oh,
we've been
had.
And then you'll
start to see
a very fast
break in the
market.
That's kind
of a
realization.
One of my
favorite stories,
it talked about
years ago when I
was on the
board of trade.
there used to
be a guy down
there, he was
a hedger for
one of the
Minneapolis grain
companies.
And that was
so many years
ago, that was a
$500 suit, was
a big deal.
But he was very
nicely dressed,
coat was always
buttoned, and
he'd be standing
there, he'd be
standing like
this, talking to
somebody, and all
of a sudden the
market would move,
one of the grain
markets would move
up or down, and
he'd very
politely excuse
himself, he'd
walk into the
crowd, and he'd
either be selling
or buying.
Well the crowd
knew, the folks
on the floor
knew he
represented size,
and all of a
sudden the
market would go
crazy for a
while.
Then he'd walk
back over,
put his hands
back behind his
back, and he'd
go back and
engage in the
conversation he'd
been in before.
Those people,
that happened to
be a very visual
example, but those
people exist in
big size.
They come in,
they're opportunists,
they come in when
markets are at
attractive levels for
them, of what they
want to do.
And nobody's going
to tell you that,
right?
Nobody's going to
tell you that, but
as you learn to
read the data, you
start to get a
better sense of what
is actually
transpiring in the
market.
And that's where
we use the market
profile graphic,
multidimensional, it
is a time-sensitive
real-time
evolving database.
Okay, so let's
move on with some
of our terminology.
What are we
looking at next?
The point of
control is
migrating lower,
and we're looking
to see as price
moves lower, it's
advertising for
what?
It's advertising
for buyers,
right?
In any business,
in any business,
the important thing
to have happen is
to find a place
where what can
take place?
Two-sided trade?
I know this
gentleman works
for Ford.
In us, there's
two-sided trade that
takes place.
Ford's not going to
sell anything,
right?
So that's what
business and price
discovery, you're
looking for those
levels, but you
want those levels
to be fair.
Now, let's take a
look at what's going
on here.
We saw the price,
we saw the
fairest price to do
business initially
migrate a little
lower.
Now, when the market
breaks late in the
day, the fairest price
in this example did
not migrate lower.
the fairest price
did not migrate
lower.
So you're coming
down here, and the
fact that it didn't
migrate lower is also
a very valuable piece
of information.
We talk about
situations where
people get caught
short in a
marketplace.
When the point of
control doesn't
migrate lower, but
price goes lower, and
it may be because
there's some rumor,
somebody said
something on CNBC,
and everybody's
going to sell, or
it hits some
technical level that
brings in all kind
of sellers, and
you're looking, if
you're looking just
at price, and most
people cannot trade
successfully because
they are too trapped
by price.
They can't put the
price in context.
But you look here,
in this example, price
goes lower, it's
trying to find, it's
trying to find a
place for two-sided
trade to take place.
It's advertising, it's
advertising down here
for buyers, but the
fairest price to do
business is up here.
When this kind of
situation happens, how
many people have heard
the term short in the
hole?
When you talk about
somebody, market people,
being short in the hole,
all that means is
you're being short,
you're getting short
at bad prices.
That's common
parlance that you hear
for years around the
trading community.
When you get people
caught short in the
hole, it means they
got emotionally trapped,
they got short at
very bad prices, and
at that point in time,
watch out, you have a
potential disaster on
your hand.
So this clue up here,
the point of control is
not going lower, let's
take a look at where
we go next with this.
And the people that
know me know that I
prefer to talk about
things that have
actually happened, and
that I've written about
or put out notices
ahead of time, because
I don't like to ever be
thought of as cherry
picking, trying to find
examples and make it
fit.
In this particular day,
the point of control,
this is real,
you see this going
down, it's not uncommon
to have this line be
almost a 45 degree line,
don't make it exact like
that.
But in the last four
periods, price is trading
lower, but the point of
control is not migrating
lower, traders are getting
short in the hole.
Look at the point of
control, the date was
April 21st, 2010.
Okay, let's take a look
what happened.
This is an email sent at
251, I advise two hedge
funds.
I advise three trading
companies in Chicago and
two hedge funds.
this is an email sent, and you
can see the time and the
day.
Look at the POC not
migrating lower, sellers are
getting caught short in the
hole, 45 degree line.
And then I say here, no
outside event, and we could be
setting up for a route.
Meaning no outside event, no
exogenous event, no unexpected
announcement.
Okay, so this is actual, there's
the date that's going to be
reproduced.
Let's back up for one second.
Look at the profile, so you
see the profile, you see this
thing setting up.
Now imagine yourself as a
trader getting caught here,
because what is price doing?
Okay, price is just going
lower and lower and lower.
A lot of traders, what happens
to a lot of traders that got on
short early in the morning, and
let's say this thing's going
down, they love it, right?
And Keith, what tendency might
you do at this point?
You start pressing it, right?
You got, and I know because
I've seen you trade, you got,
you start off here, and you're
pressing it, you're pressing
it, you're pressing it, and
it's feeling pretty good, because
price is going your way.
You're patting yourself on the
back, and sometimes not
recognizing the trap that is
building.
Okay, there's the caper, there's
the low.
We make the low, point and
control didn't go, look what
happens late in the day.
We rally all the way back to
the point of control.
The value area, again, we
introduced it briefly earlier.
It's where approximately 70%
of the daily trade takes place.
Okay?
And there's nothing, there's
nothing magical about it.
It's just a way to think
about the market, and to think
about price versus value.
One of the things you'll hear
from us consistently is we trade
value, not price.
The day we're seeing follow, it's
completed, the profile graphic
reveals the value area.
This is calculated for you.
Terry, are you here?
Terry is back there.
Terry Liverman owns a company
called Window Trader.
We get these, we use Window
Trader, and it calculates the value
area for you.
As you become more efficient, you
will start to visualize what the
market profile will look like
prior to the end of the day.
Now, when we're talking about
really becoming a successful
trader, one of the things we say is
visualize, don't predict.
So, for example, you've had just a
little introduction.
Let's say that we have a market
that opens, and it's got a pretty
aggressive buying tail right off the
opening in the morning, and the
market starts to auction higher.
Okay?
You start to visualize this is a
pretty strong day, and you start
to see that this market's moving
higher.
You start to visualize what the
profile's going to look like.
Now, you're not at that level yet,
but this is ultimately where you
want to get to.
The faster you can visualize what
the completed profile is going to
look like when the day is over,
the better you're going to be able
to position the trades, the better
you're going to be able to control
your risk in this whole situation.
So, this is the goal.
This is just kind of a normal
profile.
We don't get many of these.
We don't get many of these, but
we're just using it to keep bringing
the idea back.
Okay.
Incomplete auctions are revealed
through the profile shape.
Here, we have the low made early.
The D auction opens and begins to
complete, completes the profile.
Look over here.
That would be your initial balance
and just a little more.
As you get more comfortable with the profile
and you get more comfortable with the range
of a particular stock or future you're trading,
all of a sudden, you may look at a very narrow range like this
and you say, wait a minute, it's highly unlikely
that the range is going to be that tight
for the remainder of the day.
So, if you see this
and you look at this example,
you have a buying tail.
You don't have any completion up here.
Now, it's not always completed.
It doesn't always fit perfectly.
But, when you look at this,
you see that the buyers were more aggressive
than were the what?
Than were the sellers, right?
So, now, you say, wait a minute,
let's take a look at what's going on here.
Unlikely, we're going to hold that balance.
So, the first thing you ought to be thinking about
is opportunity.
You ought to be thinking about, wait a minute,
is there an opportunity setting up?
Years ago, when I used to advise
a lot of the folks on the Board of Trade,
I used to say, when you saw a quiet market like this,
here's what the Board of Trade guys used to do.
When you had a quiet market like this in the first period,
they'd go out and have coffee, right?
They'd go out and have coffee.
There's nothing going on.
Same thing happens to me.
I'm in front of the machine, nothing going on.
I go down and make some cereal or something.
No, no.
When you've got this,
my statement ought to be, guys,
do not go out for coffee.
The hair on the back of your neck
ought to be standing straight up.
Because there ought to be
a significant opportunity
beginning to develop here.
It's unlikely you're going to hold that range for the day.
So, we have a buying tail on the bottom.
We don't have anything earlier.
Earlier, one of the slides you saw,
when you don't have a selling tail,
you have an auction that's not completed.
Not as simple as that.
But then, now you look and you say,
wait a minute, what happens?
We introduced our term earlier called range extension.
Now, what happens?
The market's creeping up in here.
You had some evidence of buying early,
not completed.
All of a sudden, in the D period,
the market comes to life.
We come out of this narrow range.
We come out of this narrow range,
and as we would say,
the market goes bit.
All of a sudden,
the market has come in.
The bidders are there.
Price is going higher.
And you can see D period,
E, F, G, H, I.
Let me introduce this term right here for a second.
We have a term that we call one time framing.
One time framing is nothing more
than when one period,
and let's say it's one time framing up,
one period does not take out the low of the prior period,
does either stay within the range
or take out the high.
So, in the market,
the auction starts here,
pretty aggressive.
And remember,
I can split these profiles out at any point.
You've seen completed profiles,
but I also can split them out.
So, when something changes here,
it gets aggressive.
There we go.
The D period.
Did E period take out the low of D period?
No.
Did F period take out the low of E period?
Did G period take out the low of F period?
Did H?
No.
I?
Okay?
And J did not.
You came up in balance in J.
So,
for 30,
60,
90,
120,
150,
you can go on up,
that once the market got started here,
the market one time framed up
for
all the way through the J period
and close to the end of the day.
I was shocked
as this has always been
a very natural thing to me.
I was shocked
the first time
I had a room
of probably 50 to 60
professional traders
and I asked the question
how many people
understand what one time framing is
and I got one response.
I was shocked
because it is just
such a helpful thing
to know
what is going on
because
what happens
if you understand this,
you don't fade
and fade
means going against the market.
So,
in this direction,
the market,
the auction is going which way?
The going is higher,
right?
The biggest single mistake
that traders make
is fading a trend day
or fading a market
that's one time framing
higher or lower.
Now,
if you fall into the trap
because it was quiet
to begin with,
right?
You fall into the trap,
the market's going higher
and you think,
oh boy,
you know,
if I could have sold this thing
at 10 this morning,
I didn't.
But boy,
at 18,
it looks like a real sell
here at 18.
Intuitively,
you just say,
oh boy,
I got to sell it here.
We're programmed to think
that that's less risk
and it actually,
if it's one time framing up,
you're taking
a tremendous amount of risk.
Intuitively,
you don't think that.
You think,
well,
I've got less risk
selling something
at 8 than I do at 6.
Not necessarily true
if the market's
one time framing up.
When you see
something like this,
one of the things
you're trying to learn
to do is just
go with it.
We make more errors
by outthinking ourselves,
by fighting against
what the market's
actually doing.
And it doesn't make any,
we've got a room
of people here today
that run from
extremely experienced
to very inexperienced.
But I will promise you,
because I know
an awful lot
of very experienced
traders,
we make the same mistake.
We get it in our head
that something's
not worth something
and we sit down there
and we do something
like this,
the day is over
and we look at
why we weren't successful
and we say,
how in the world
could I have done that?
Because we got
something else
in our mind,
we weren't objectively
looking at the market
generated information.
do not short a market
that's one time
framing up.
Anyhow,
we get off in tangents
but that's alright.
We started,
we take the completed day,
we started down here,
we had a buying tail,
we had an uncompleted profile,
a very narrow base,
they came into the market
and all of a sudden
the auction started
to go higher.
Now there's a lot
more information
in here,
a lot more information.
but I just want you
to kind of get
a feel
of what's going on
and introducing
the phrase
of one time frame.
Let's kind of continue
on with our example.
Again,
you've heard this before,
in the old days
when,
I used to have
a discount futures firm,
JF Dalton Associates,
and in those days
there's most
of the early business
and there were
a lot of floor traders
on the market.
The really good
floor traders
developed a skill
and that skill
was listening
to the market.
Okay,
if you went up
to yesterday's high,
you went up
to yesterday's high
and we all know
that floor traders
might play games,
what are you going to have
at yesterday's high?
You're going to have stops.
Okay,
a great game
for the floor trader
at that point in time
was to bid the market up
to get the stops.
Once you get the stops,
you force people to buy.
If you're a floor trader,
how do you profit
from hitting the stops
by selling into it, right?
You bid it up,
you force the stops to cover,
you now sold.
All right?
Now,
if that's as simple
as it was,
what would happen?
The floor traders
would bid the market up,
they would hear
the level of,
the orders are coming
into the pit
or what we call
the outside flow of orders
or the lack
of outside flow of orders.
So the market comes in,
you take out
yesterday's high,
this, I said,
means buy
on the floor.
So you go up,
you take out
yesterday's high,
you hit the stops
and all of a sudden
it gets deathly quiet.
It gets deathly quiet,
what does that tell you?
There is no more
flow of orders
from the outside.
So the good floor trader
intuitively went from
buy,
hands out,
means sell.
He heard the market,
he heard there was
no outside flow of orders.
Okay?
Gave him a tremendous advantage.
Now,
you take out
yesterday's high
and the level of volume
increases tremendously.
So,
higher prices
instead of cutting off
activity,
the level goes up,
the bids are coming in,
so that's bringing in
more orders.
It gets very noisy,
keeps bidding,
but they heard
that go on.
Okay?
Now,
the floor,
so much of the business
on the floors
has gone away.
That advantage
to the floor trader
is gone.
My single biggest
client base
has been
among floor traders
that were transitioning
from the floor
to learning to trade
upstairs
off of electronic screens.
It's a totally
new business tool.
They lost the ability
to hear
what was going on
on the floor of the market.
When that happens
and when you're learning
to trade
from an electronic screen
upstairs,
what you start to do
is you start to
replace hearing
with understanding
structure
and how structure
builds
in there.
The structure,
the structure
is your weight.
In other words,
you,
what you used to hear,
you now develop
an ability
to see.
Some of the
more experienced
foreign traders,
they could tell you,
for example,
right down here
in the low,
if this is the opening price,
they could tell you
if this was the low,
they could look at it,
they can't hear it anymore,
but they can still hear it
in their mind.
The bids were pretty aggressive.
So,
now,
I just want to look
at some ideas
of structure.
We're not going to cover
this in any detail
just yet,
but when I see
a structure
that goes
thin on the bottom
and it starts
to look like
the letter P
on top,
if you have
don't know
anything about
what we're talking about
doesn't mean
anything to you,
but
from experience,
I know
that when I have
a P shape
in the structure,
that is an indication
that I have
short covering.
Okay?
Another way
we refer to
short covering
is old business.
In other words,
the people
that have already
been short,
how do you
cover a short?
If you've been short,
you have to buy
in order to
cover that short.
That is old business.
You're closing out
something you already had
versus new business.
If you came in
to buy something
for the first time,
that would be
new business.
The visualized structure,
if you had
a market
started out
like this
at the bottom
with a relatively
thin structure
and you had
a combination
of short covering
and almost all
rallies begin
with short covering
and they had
that short covering
joined by
new buying
so you had
old business
combined with
new business,
then more than likely
what's going to
happen to your structure,
it's going to
elongate out
because you've got
two different kinds
of business
coming in.
When your structure
doesn't elongate
and you start
to get the formation
that looks like
the letter P,
you had
old business,
the old business
was coming in,
people were covering
shorts,
but it wasn't
joined by
new business.
When you look
over on the
right side,
let's go all the way
from the left
to the right,
let's take the
mirror image
of short covering
would be
long liquidation.
So let's say
you have traders
that have gotten
too long,
for example,
momentum traders
that have gotten
too long
and all of a sudden
the liquidation
starts,
but it's liquidation
not joined by
new fresh shorts
in the market,
it's just liquidating
a long position,
you tend to get
the mirror image
of the P formation
which is the letter B.
Okay?
Now,
again,
there's not enough
information for you
to take and use
yet with that
other than to have
increase your
understanding
of what is going
on in the
marketplace.
For example,
here's a tough one
that most people
have a lot of
difficulty with.
Does short covering,
after the short
covering is completed,
does it strengthen
or weaken
a market?
How many people
think it strengthens
the market?
Okay?
And how many people
think it weakens
the market?
And how many people
don't know?
Okay?
Short covering,
when the short
covering is over,
it actually weakens
the underlying
structure of the market.
Because if somebody's
short,
what do they have to do
to cover their short?
They have to buy,
right?
And once you take
that buy,
that buy inventory
out of the market,
you've actually weakened
the underlying structure
of the market.
It's only one data point.
But it's something
to remember.
When you have
long liquidation,
okay,
when you get the
long liquidation,
again,
it's kind of
the mirror image.
Again,
we are just touching
on concepts.
There's far more
to it than this.
I'm just kind of
walking you along
to get some idea
of the importance
of understanding
the structure
of a market.
And that there is
structure to a market.
Just as there's structure,
if you go to Sotheby's
for an auction,
there is structure
to the way
that auction is handled.
They have rules,
they have regulations,
they have a procedure
for that auction.
Any auction you go to
will have some kind
of structure to it.
Now,
the day in the middle,
the structure in the middle,
the two books
you should read,
I've written two books.
The first one
was called
Mind Over Markets.
Mind Over Markets,
the first book,
is more linear.
Traders seem to enjoy
that market,
that book more
because it feels
more linear,
it feels more understandable,
the definitions
aren't as ambiguous
in it.
The second book
is called
Markets in Profile.
The best book
is actually
Markets in Profile.
It's more ambiguous,
it's harder to understand,
but guess what?
The harder it is
to understand,
the fewer people
that are going
to stick with it,
the greater the edge
that you're going
to get with it.
You need to read
both books.
But,
the first book
is more mechanical,
we've changed
the terms,
when I wrote
the first book,
Mind Over Markets,
I basically
used the terms
that were introduced
to me by
Pete Stonelmeyer
who introduced
this concept
to begin with.
As I got
more experience,
I'm not as comfortable
with the terms,
so I've renamed
the terms.
The first term
to start with
is what I call
a primary,
a primary day.
In other words,
when I call it
a primary day,
it's a day
that we have
a tendency
to see
more often.
It's a more
common type
of day.
In this day,
you'll see the high
was made in B period,
you see the point
of control
in the center,
you see a little bit
of range extension
to the downside.
It's kind of the day
I use to measure
other days
against now.
While we're at it,
it's a nuance.
One of the things
that you'll hear
from us
multiple times
is the importance
of nuances.
Nuances make
a huge amount
of difference.
Unsuccessful traders
have a tendency
to skip over nuances.
You ever have somebody
that's not telling
you the truth?
They tell you
a story,
they look in your eyes,
and they just
intuitively know
that you didn't
quite buy their story.
What do they do next?
They kind of repeat
themselves, right?
themselves.
They kind of tell you
the story again,
and they put just
a little bit
of different twist,
a little bit different
twist on it.
And there's information,
there's information
in that.
And you start to read
that kind of information.
Is it real?
Are they telling me
the truth?
Aren't they telling me
You need,
when you look
at the market,
you need some way
to judge,
is what you're seeing
in price
the real truth
behind what is going
on in the market?
So many times,
the information
is in a nuance.
Just as the person
that didn't tell you
the truth
tends to talk
a little bit more
and tends to repeat
the story,
the nuance is they're
probably not telling
the truth.
Nuances do matter.
Nuances separate out
the winners and the losers.
I always liked the example.
I had a very good,
very good friend
when I was in the service
that really desperately
wanted to be
a professional football player.
He played for Xavier.
And he said,
he said,
Jim,
I think what kept me back,
he said,
I was probably
just a fraction
of a second
too slow
to get through the hole.
He was very well built,
very athletic,
but he said,
just a fraction.
And sometimes,
it's just a fraction
that makes the difference
between winning
and losing.
So nuances are important.
Being able to look
at a particular day
like this
and have some base
against which to judge
other nuances
is very important.
Side while we're on here,
very minor,
but if you go back,
and I don't ask
anybody here
to take
what I say
for granted.
I want you
to take
and go take it back,
study it,
and make the evaluation
on your own.
I'm going to guess,
and I've not done this
mathematically
and systematically,
I'm going to guess
that probably
about someplace
in the order of
75 to 80 percent
of the time,
the high or low
of a day
is made
within the first
hour or so.
In this particular day,
we have A period,
B period,
the high was made,
the high was made
early in the morning.
We didn't set this up,
I just looked at it
right here.
The low was made
early in the morning.
Up there,
the high was made,
not a completed high,
but it's made
early in the morning.
But it's just something,
it's a nuance
to go back,
look at,
and think about.
There's very valuable
information in some of that.
Now, price will mess you
up throughout the day,
you'll forget about that.
But if you keep that in mind,
it can be very helpful.
Okay?
Just an idea
of some of the structure.
We look here,
one of the things
that we talked about earlier,
here's April 9th,
we see the market
break,
this was a Friday,
this market
was absolutely
dead quiet
until very late
in the day.
And I hope somebody
will tell me
that's a Friday,
I hope I remember correctly.
And late in the day,
the market broke
to the upside.
The following Monday,
the market remained
within that upper section.
When markets make
big price moves
up or down,
it usually takes
sometimes the process
before it reverses itself.
Here's what's important.
This structure,
remember earlier,
we talked about
to get away
and remain away
from the fairest price
in which business
is being conducted.
Is it more than likely
going to take volume?
What if it moves away
from the fairest price
to conduct business
but it's not on volume?
The chances are
that you're not going
to be able
to hold that.
It's the same thing.
We're a gentleman
from Ford.
Ford raises the price
of the new Ford Focus.
They raise it too high.
Guess what?
They're not going
to be able
to hold that level.
You'll get some
financing break
or some cash back.
But sometimes,
they're not going
to do it immediately, right?
If a manufacturer
raises a price
that's too high,
you know,
he doesn't get
the information
the next day,
sometimes it may take
a few days
or some time
to sink in.
The difference is
everything happens
exactly the same way.
In the markets,
it seems to happen
far quicker sometimes
than it does
in a manufacturing organization.
But this day,
the market
was not elongating out.
It probably caught
some short,
some game playing
late in the day.
The market went up
on low volume.
We held that volume
on Monday
and take a look
what happened
on Tuesday.
So we came back down
and listen,
remember the early slide
I was showing you,
I used a term
called repair.
Early on,
I was saying,
here's one of the things
we're going to get to
by the time
we get through
the seminar.
When you have
poor structure,
and this is poor structure,
there's no elongation,
that didn't go up
on good volume,
you balanced
on the following day
and you came back down
and you repaired
this structure.
So this whole thing
was corrected
a couple of days later.
Now,
here's what happens
to traders
very often.
they don't have
the patience
to recognize
that this
is an opportunity
that is setting up.
But that
opportunity
may take
some time
to develop.
But let's talk
about odds
for a second.
If this,
if you're lucky,
let's say you're lucky
and you caught
this spike
late in the day,
you got the spike
to the upside
and you caught it
and when you go home
on Friday
and you're long
and you're profit,
how do you feel?
You feel pretty good.
You know,
you're walking around,
you're kind of
bouncing around
at the top of the world.
This is pretty neat.
I'm a pretty good trader.
You kind of pat yourself
on the back.
Oblivious
to how much risk
that you really have.
One of the things
that we talk about
with traders
and
when I first
say this statement,
I can look
in the eyes
of the people
I'm talking to
and I can tell
if they have any idea
what I'm saying
or not.
I can also have
a pretty good idea
their chances
of success
down the road.
Most people
are trading
and their objective
is just to make money.
Can you manage return?
You can't manage return.
The markets,
whatever the market does,
you can't affect that.
It's going to do
what it's going to do.
You cannot manage return.
However,
you can manage your risk.
You can manage
the risk you take.
If you learn
to manage your risk,
which you can manage,
but you cannot manage
your return,
all of a sudden
you have made
a huge breakthrough.
I said earlier
I advise
two hedge funds.
One hedge fund
has been profitable
for ten years.
they got hurt
in the break
a few years ago.
First time we had lunch
they wanted to talk
about, you know,
kind of getting
the business rebuilt.
We talked about it
and I made this same thing
about you can manage,
you can manage risk,
but you can't manage return.
I could just see
kind of the blank
look at the lunch,
what was going on.
One of the principles
of this firm
was a basketball player
for Utah.
Very knowledgeable,
very intelligent trader.
But it really didn't
sink in at first.
We talked about this
about a year later.
I get a copy,
I get a copy
of a letter
that he sent
to his partner.
His partner identified
me and brought me in.
He said,
the best thing
you ever did to us
was introducing
Jim into the equation.
He said,
because it didn't
make a lot of sense
to me at lunch
when he first said it,
but it's made
all the difference
to how we manage
the money
and to our return.
It finally got,
what he was saying,
is we can't manage risk.
And where we got hurt
the first time,
we weren't managing risk.
We were after return.
He said,
now we know
how to manage risk.
And he said,
the return
is falling into,
is falling into place.
It took a while
for that to sink in.
It was a very sincere compliment.
This guy does not
pass out compliments
for anything.
It took a period of time
for it to sink in.
to restructure
how the entire fund
was managed.
But it all came
down to managing risk.
Now,
I got another notice
from him the other day,
and I may have the numbers
somewhat wrong,
but when the market
was down big,
over 1,000 point
and ended up down,
what, about 300, 400?
The market, I think,
was off someplace
in the 3% area.
And if I remember right,
their fund was off 0.4%.
That's a big,
that's a big change.
We talk about managing risk.
And that came about
because when this exogenous
event took place,
exogenous just means
something that's outside
of anybody's model
for running their portfolio
or running their account.
When this exogenous event
took place the other day,
because they had managed risk,
their loss was minimal.
You talk,
if you're running
an awful lot of money
and you start to get,
you know,
a couple percent difference
in, that's big money.
Thank you.